EVERY object in the next day’s journey was new and interesting to Elizabeth; and her spirits
were in a state of enjoyment; for she had seen her sister looking so well as to banish
all fear for her health, and the prospect of her northern tour was a constant source of delight.
When they left the high road for the lane to Hunsford, every eye was in search of
the Parsonage, and every turning expected to bring it in view. The paling of Rosings
park was their boundary on one side. Elizabeth smiled at the recollection
of all that she had heard of its inhabitants. At length the Parsonage was discernible. The
garden sloping to the road, the house standing in it, the green pales and the laurel hedge,
everything declared they were arriving. Mr. Collins and Charlotte appeared at the door,
and the carriage stopped at the small gate, which led by a short gravel walk to the house,
amidst the nods and smiles of the whole party. In a moment they were all out of the chaise,
rejoicing at the sight of each other. Mrs. Collins welcomed her friend with the liveliest pleasure,
and Elizabeth was more and more satisfied with coming, when she found herself so affectionately
received. She saw instantly that her cousin’s manners were not altered by his marriage: his
formal civility was just what it had been; and he detained her some minutes at the gate to hear and
satisfy his inquiries after all her family. They were then, with no other delay than his pointing
out the neatness of the entrance, taken into the house; and as soon as they were in the parlour,
he welcomed them a second time, with ostentatious formality, to his humble abode, and punctually
repeated all his wife’s offers of refreshment. Elizabeth was prepared to see him in his glory;
and she could not help fancying that in displaying the good proportion of the room,
its aspect, and its furniture, he addressed himself particularly to her, as if wishing to
make her feel what she had lost in refusing him. But though everything seemed neat and comfortable,
she was not able to gratify him by any sigh of repentance; and rather looked with wonder at
her friend, that she could have so cheerful an air with such a companion. When Mr. Collins said
anything of which his wife might reasonably be ashamed, which certainly was not seldom,
she involuntarily turned her eye on Charlotte. Once or twice she could discern a faint blush;
but in general Charlotte wisely did not hear. After sitting long enough to admire every article
of furniture in the room, from the sideboard to the fender, to give an account of their journey,
and of all that had happened in London, Mr. Collins invited them to take a stroll in the
garden, which was large and well laid out, and to the cultivation of which he attended himself.
To work in his garden was one of his most respectable pleasures; and Elizabeth admired
the command of countenance with which Charlotte talked of the healthfulness of the exercise, and
owned she encouraged it as much as possible. Here, leading the way through every walk and cross walk,
and scarcely allowing them an interval to utter the praises he asked for, every view was pointed
out with a minuteness which left beauty entirely behind. He could number the fields in every
direction, and could tell how many trees there were in the most distant clump. But of all the
views which his garden, or which the country or the kingdom could boast, none were to be compared
with the prospect of Rosings, afforded by an opening in the trees that bordered the park nearly
opposite the front of his house. It was a handsome modern building, well situated on rising ground.
From his garden, Mr. Collins would have led them round his two meadows; but the ladies,
not having shoes to encounter the remains of a white frost, turned back; and while Sir William
accompanied him, Charlotte took her sister and friend over the house, extremely well pleased,
probably, to have the opportunity of showing it without her husband’s help. It was rather small,
but well built and convenient; and everything was fitted up and arranged with a neatness
and consistency, of which Elizabeth gave Charlotte all the credit. When
Mr. Collins could be forgotten, there was really a great air of comfort throughout,
and by Charlotte’s evident enjoyment of it, Elizabeth supposed he must be often forgotten.
She had already learnt that Lady Catherine was still in the country. It was spoken of
again while they were at dinner, when Mr. Collins joining in, observed,—
“Yes, Miss Elizabeth, you will have the honour of seeing Lady Catherine de Bourgh
on the ensuing Sunday at church, and I need not say you will be delighted with her. She is all
affability and condescension, and I doubt not but you will be honoured with some portion of
her notice when service is over. I have scarcely any hesitation in saying that she will include
you and my sister Maria in every invitation with which she honours us during your stay here. Her
behaviour to my dear Charlotte is charming. We dine at Rosings twice every week, and are never
allowed to walk home. Her Ladyship’s carriage is regularly ordered for us. I should say, one of her
Ladyship’s carriages, for she has several.” “Lady Catherine is a very respectable,
sensible woman, indeed,” added Charlotte, “and a most attentive neighbour.”
“Very true, my dear, that is exactly what I say. She is the sort of woman whom one
cannot regard with too much deference.” The evening was spent chiefly in talking
over Hertfordshire news, and telling again what had been already written; and when it closed,
Elizabeth, in the solitude of her chamber, had to meditate upon Charlotte’s degree of contentment,
to understand her address in guiding, and composure in bearing with, her husband, and
to acknowledge that it was all done very well. She had also to anticipate how her visit would pass,
the quiet tenour of their usual employments, the vexatious interruptions of Mr. Collins,
and the gaieties of their intercourse with Rosings. A lively imagination soon settled it all.
About the middle of the next day, as she was in her room getting ready for a walk,
a sudden noise below seemed to speak the whole house in confusion; and, after listening a moment,
she heard somebody running upstairs in a violent hurry, and calling loudly after her. She opened
the door, and met Maria in the landing-place, who, breathless with agitation, cried out,—
“Oh, my dear Eliza! pray make haste
and come into the dining-room, for there is such a sight to be seen! I will not tell you what it is.
Make haste, and come down this moment.” Elizabeth asked questions in vain;
Maria would tell her nothing more; and down they ran into the dining-room which fronted the lane,
in quest of this wonder; it was two ladies, stopping in a low phaeton at the garden gate.
“And is this all?” cried Elizabeth. “I expected at least that the pigs were got into the garden,
and here is nothing but Lady Catherine and her daughter!”
“La! my dear,” said Maria, quite shocked at the mistake, “it is not Lady Catherine.
The old lady is Mrs. Jenkinson, who lives with them. The other is Miss De Bourgh. Only look at
her. She is quite a little creature. Who would have thought she could be so thin and small!”
“She is abominably rude to keep Charlotte out of doors in all this wind. Why does she not come in?”
“Oh, Charlotte says she hardly ever does.
It is the greatest of favours when Miss De Bourgh comes in.”
“I like her appearance,” said Elizabeth, struck with other ideas. “She looks sickly
and cross. Yes, she will do for him very well. She will make him a very proper wife.”
Mr. Collins and Charlotte were both standing at the gate in conversation with the ladies; and
Sir William, to Elizabeth’s high diversion, was stationed in the doorway, in earnest contemplation
of the greatness before him, and constantly bowing whenever Miss De Bourgh looked that way.
At length there was nothing more to be said; the ladies drove on, and the others returned
into the house. Mr. Collins no sooner saw the two girls than he began to congratulate them on their
good fortune, which Charlotte explained by letting them know that the whole party was asked to dine
at Rosings the next day.
“Lady Catherine, said she, you have given me a treasure.”
CHAPTER XXIX.
MR. COLLINS’S triumph, in consequence of this invitation, was complete. The power of
displaying the grandeur of his patroness to his wondering visitors, and of letting them
see her civility towards himself and his wife, was exactly what he had wished for;
and that an opportunity of doing it should be given so soon was such an instance of
Lady Catherine’s condescension as he knew not how to admire enough.
“I confess,” said he, “that I should not have been at all surprised by her Ladyship’s asking
us on Sunday to drink tea and spend the evening at Rosings. I rather expected,
from my knowledge of her affability, that it would happen. But who could have foreseen such
an attention as this? Who could have imagined that we should receive an invitation to dine
there (an invitation, moreover, including the whole party) so immediately after your arrival?”
“I am the less surprised at what has happened,” replied Sir William,
“from that knowledge of what the manners of the great really are, which my situation in life
has allowed me to acquire. About the court, such instances of elegant breeding are not uncommon.”
Scarcely anything was talked of the whole day or next morning but their visit to Rosings.
Mr. Collins was carefully instructing them in what they were to expect, that the sight of such rooms,
so many servants, and so splendid a dinner, might not wholly overpower them.
When the ladies were separating for the toilette, he said to Elizabeth,—
“Do not make yourself uneasy, my dear cousin, about your apparel. Lady Catherine is far from
requiring that elegance of dress in us which becomes herself and daughter. I would advise
you merely to put on whatever of your clothes is superior to the rest—there
is no occasion for anything more. Lady Catherine will not think the worse of
you for being simply dressed. She likes to have the distinction of rank preserved.”
While they were dressing, he came two or three times to their different doors, to recommend
their being quick, as Lady Catherine very much objected to be kept waiting for her dinner.
Such formidable accounts of her Ladyship, and her manner of living, quite frightened Maria Lucas,
who had been little used to company; and she looked forward to her introduction at Rosings
with as much apprehension as her father had done to his presentation at St. James’s.
As the weather was fine, they had a pleasant walk of about half a mile across the park.
Every park has its beauty and its prospects; and Elizabeth saw much to be pleased with,
though she could not be in such raptures as Mr. Collins expected the scene to inspire,
and was but slightly affected by his enumeration of the windows in front of the house, and his
relation of what the glazing altogether had originally cost Sir Lewis de Bourgh.
When they ascended the steps to the hall, Maria’s alarm was every moment increasing, and even Sir
William did not look perfectly calm. Elizabeth’s courage did not fail her. She had heard nothing of
Lady Catherine that spoke her awful from any extraordinary talents or miraculous virtue,
and the mere stateliness of money and rank she thought she could witness without trepidation.
From the entrance hall, of which Mr. Collins pointed out, with a rapturous air,
the fine proportion and finished ornaments, they followed the servants through an antechamber to
the room where Lady Catherine, her daughter, and Mrs. Jenkinson were sitting. Her Ladyship,
with great condescension, arose to receive them; and as Mrs. Collins had settled it with her
husband that the office of introduction should be hers, it was performed in a proper manner,
without any of those apologies and thanks which he would have thought necessary.
In spite of having been at St. James’s, Sir William was so completely awed by the
grandeur surrounding him, that he had but just courage enough to make a very low bow,
and take his seat without saying a word; and his daughter, frightened almost out of her senses,
sat on the edge of her chair, not knowing which way to look. Elizabeth found herself quite equal
to the scene, and could observe the three ladies before her composedly. Lady Catherine was a tall,
large woman, with strongly-marked features, which might once have been handsome. Her air
was not conciliating, nor was her manner of receiving them such as to make her visitors
forget their inferior rank. She was not rendered formidable by silence: but whatever
she said was spoken in so authoritative a tone as marked her self-importance, and brought Mr.
Wickham immediately to Elizabeth’s mind; and, from the observation of the day altogether,
she believed Lady Catherine to be exactly what he had represented.
When, after examining the mother, in whose countenance and deportment she soon found
some resemblance of Mr. Darcy, she turned her eyes on the daughter, she could almost have
joined in Maria’s astonishment at her being so thin and so small. There was neither in figure
nor face any likeness between the ladies. Miss de Bourgh was pale and sickly: her features,
though not plain, were insignificant; and she spoke very little, except in a low voice,
to Mrs. Jenkinson, in whose appearance there was nothing remarkable, and who was entirely
engaged in listening to what she said, and placing a screen in the proper direction before her eyes.
After sitting a few minutes, they were all sent to one of the windows to admire the view,
Mr. Collins attending them to point out its beauties,
and Lady Catherine kindly informing them that it was much better worth looking at in the summer.
The dinner was exceedingly handsome, and there were all the servants,
and all the articles of plate which Mr. Collins had promised; and, as he had likewise foretold,
he took his seat at the bottom of the table, by her Ladyship’s desire, and looked as if he felt
that life could furnish nothing greater. He carved and ate and praised with delighted alacrity;
and every dish was commended first by him, and then by Sir William, who was now enough
recovered to echo whatever his son-in-law said, in a manner which Elizabeth wondered
Lady Catherine could bear. But Lady Catherine seemed gratified by their excessive admiration,
and gave most gracious smiles, especially when any dish on the table proved a novelty to them.
The party did not supply much conversation. Elizabeth was ready to speak whenever there was
an opening, but she was seated between Charlotte and Miss de Bourgh—the former of whom was engaged
in listening to Lady Catherine, and the latter said not a word to her all the dinnertime.
Mrs. Jenkinson was chiefly employed in watching how little Miss de Bourgh ate, pressing her to try
some other dish and fearing she was indisposed. Maria thought speaking out of the question,
and the gentlemen did nothing but eat and admire. When the ladies returned to the drawing-room,
there was little to be done but to hear Lady Catherine talk, which she did without any
intermission till coffee came in, delivering her opinion on every subject in so decisive a
manner as proved that she was not used to have her judgment controverted. She inquired into
Charlotte’s domestic concerns familiarly and minutely, and gave her a great deal of advice
as to the management of them all; told her how everything ought to be regulated in so
small a family as hers, and instructed her as to the care of her cows and her poultry.
Elizabeth found that nothing was beneath this great lady’s attention which could furnish her
with an occasion for dictating to others. In the intervals of her discourse with Mrs. Collins,
she addressed a variety of questions to Maria and Elizabeth, but especially to the latter,
of whose connections she knew the least, and who, she observed to Mrs. Collins, was a very genteel,
pretty kind of girl. She asked her at different times how many sisters she had, whether they were
older or younger than herself, whether any of them were likely to be married, whether
they were handsome, where they had been educated, what carriage her father kept, and what had been
her mother’s maiden name? Elizabeth felt all the impertinence of her questions, but answered them
very composedly. Lady Catherine then observed,— “Your father’s estate is entailed on Mr. Collins,
I think? For your sake,” turning to Charlotte, “I am glad of it; but otherwise I see no occasion for
entailing estates from the female line. It was not thought necessary in Sir Lewis de Bourgh’s family.
Do you play and sing, Miss Bennet?” “A little.”
“Oh then—some time or other we shall be happy to hear you. Our instrument is a capital one,
probably superior to —— you shall try it some day. Do your sisters play and sing?”
“One of them does.” “Why did not you all learn? You ought all to have
learned. The Miss Webbs all play, and their father has not so good an income as yours. Do you draw?”
“No, not at all.” “What, none of you?”
“Not one.” “That is very strange. But I suppose you had
no opportunity. Your mother should have taken you to town every spring for the benefit of masters.”
“My mother would have no objection, but my father hates London.”
“Has your governess left you?” “We never had any governess.”
“No governess! How was that possible? Five daughters brought up at home without a governess!
I never heard of such a thing. Your mother must have been quite a slave to your education.”
Elizabeth could hardly help smiling, as she assured her that had not been the case.
“Then who taught you? who attended to you? Without a governess, you must have been neglected.”
“Compared with some families, I believe we were; but such of us as wished to learn never wanted
the means. We were always encouraged to read, and had all the masters that were necessary.
Those who chose to be idle certainly might.” “Ay, no doubt: but that is what a governess
will prevent; and if I had known your mother, I should have advised her most strenuously to engage
one. I always say that nothing is to be done in education without steady and regular instruction,
and nobody but a governess can give it. It is wonderful how many families I have been
the means of supplying in that way. I am always glad to get a young person well placed out. Four
nieces of Mrs. Jenkinson are most delightfully situated through my means; and it was but the
other day that I recommended another young person, who was merely accidentally mentioned to me,
and the family are quite delighted with her. Mrs. Collins, did I tell you of Lady Metcalfe’s
calling yesterday to thank me? She finds Miss Pope a treasure. ‘Lady Catherine,’ said she,
‘you have given me a treasure.’ Are any of your younger sisters out, Miss Bennet?”
“Yes, ma’am, all.” “All!
What, all five out at once? Very odd! And you only the second. The younger ones out
before the elder are married! Your younger sisters must be very young?”
“Yes, my youngest is not sixteen. Perhaps she is full young to be much in company. But really,
ma’am, I think it would be very hard upon younger sisters that they should not have their share of
society and amusement, because the elder may not have the means or inclination to marry early. The
last born has as good a right to the pleasures of youth as the first. And to be kept back on such
a motive! I think it would not be very likely to promote sisterly affection or delicacy of mind.”
“Upon my word,” said her Ladyship, “you give your opinion very decidedly for so young a person.
Pray, what is your age?” “With three younger sisters
grown up,” replied Elizabeth, smiling, “your Ladyship can hardly expect me to own it.”
Lady Catherine seemed quite astonished at not receiving a direct answer;
and Elizabeth suspected herself to be the first creature who had ever dared to trifle
with so much dignified impertinence. “You cannot be more than twenty, I am
sure,—therefore you need not conceal your age.” “I am not one-and-twenty.”
When the gentlemen had joined them, and tea was over, the card tables were placed. Lady Catherine,
Sir William, and Mr. and Mrs. Collins sat down to quadrille; and as Miss De Bourgh chose to play at
cassino, the two girls had the honour of assisting Mrs. Jenkinson to make up her party. Their table
was superlatively stupid. Scarcely a syllable was uttered that did not relate to the game, except
when Mrs. Jenkinson expressed her fears of Miss De Bourgh’s being too hot or too cold, or having too
much or too little light. A great deal more passed at the other table. Lady Catherine was generally
speaking—stating the mistakes of the three others, or relating some anecdote of herself. Mr.
Collins was employed in agreeing to everything her Ladyship said, thanking her for every fish he won,
and apologizing if he thought he won too many. Sir William did not say much. He was storing
his memory with anecdotes and noble names. When Lady Catherine and her daughter had played
as long as they chose, the tables were broken up, the carriage was offered to Mrs. Collins,
gratefully accepted, and immediately ordered. The party then gathered round the fire to hear Lady
Catherine determine what weather they were to have on the morrow. From these instructions they were
summoned by the arrival of the coach; and with many speeches of thankfulness on Mr. Collins’s
side, and as many bows on Sir William’s, they departed. As soon as they had driven from the
door, Elizabeth was called on by her cousin to give her opinion of all that she had seen at
Rosings, which, for Charlotte’s sake, she made more favourable than it really was.
But her commendation, though costing her some trouble, could by no means satisfy Mr. Collins,
and he was very soon obliged to take her Ladyship’s praise into his own hands.
CHAPTER XXX.
SIR WILLIAM stayed only a week at Hunsford; but his visit was long enough to convince him of his
daughter’s being most comfortably settled, and of her possessing such a husband and such a neighbour
as were not often met with. While Sir William was with them, Mr. Collins devoted his mornings
to driving him out in his gig, and showing him the country: but when he went away, the whole family
returned to their usual employments, and Elizabeth was thankful to find that they did not see more of
her cousin by the alteration; for the chief of the time between breakfast and dinner was now passed
by him either at work in the garden, or in reading and writing, and looking out of window in his own
book room, which fronted the road. The room in which the ladies sat was backwards. Elizabeth at
first had rather wondered that Charlotte should not prefer the dining parlour for common use;
it was a better sized room, and had a pleasanter aspect: but she soon saw that her friend had an
excellent reason for what she did, for Mr. Collins would undoubtedly have been much less in his own
apartment had they sat in one equally lively; and she gave Charlotte credit for the arrangement.
From the drawing-room they could distinguish nothing in the lane, and were indebted to Mr.
Collins for the knowledge of what carriages went along, and how often especially Miss
De Bourgh drove by in her phaeton, which he never failed coming to inform them of,
though it happened almost every day. She not unfrequently stopped at the Parsonage, and
had a few minutes’ conversation with Charlotte, but was scarcely ever prevailed on to get out.
Very few days passed in which Mr. Collins did not walk to Rosings, and not many in which his wife
did not think it necessary to go likewise; and till Elizabeth recollected that there might be
other family livings to be disposed of, she could not understand the sacrifice of so many hours. Now
and then they were honoured with a call from her Ladyship, and nothing escaped her observation that
was passing in the room during these visits. She examined into their employments, looked at
their work, and advised them to do it differently; found fault with the arrangement of the furniture,
or detected the housemaid in negligence; and if she accepted any refreshment, seemed to do it only
for the sake of finding out that Mrs. Collins’s joints of meat were too large for her family.
Elizabeth soon perceived, that though this great lady was not in the commission of the peace for
the county, she was a most active magistrate in her own parish, the minutest concerns of
which were carried to her by Mr. Collins; and whenever any of the cottagers were disposed to
be quarrelsome, discontented, or too poor, she sallied forth into the village to settle their
differences, silence their complaints, and scold them into harmony and plenty.
“he never failed to inform them”
The entertainment of dining at Rosings was repeated about twice a week; and,
allowing for the loss of Sir William, and there being only one card-table in the evening,
every such entertainment was the counterpart of the first. Their other engagements were few,
as the style of living of the neighbourhood in general was beyond the Collinses’ reach. This,
however, was no evil to Elizabeth, and upon the whole she spent her time comfortably enough:
there were half hours of pleasant conversation with Charlotte, and the weather was so fine for
the time of year, that she had often great enjoyment out of doors. Her favourite walk,
and where she frequently went while the others were calling on Lady Catherine, was along the open
grove which edged that side of the park, where there was a nice sheltered path, which no one
seemed to value but herself, and where she felt beyond the reach of Lady Catherine’s curiosity.
In this quiet way the first fortnight of her visit soon passed away. Easter was approaching, and the
week preceding it was to bring an addition to the family at Rosings, which in so small a circle must
be important. Elizabeth had heard, soon after her arrival, that Mr. Darcy was expected there in the
course of a few weeks; and though there were not many of her acquaintance whom she did not prefer,
his coming would furnish one comparatively new to look at in their Rosings parties,
and she might be amused in seeing how hopeless Miss Bingley’s designs on him were, by his
behaviour to his cousin, for whom he was evidently destined by Lady Catherine, who talked of his
coming with the greatest satisfaction, spoke of him in terms of the highest admiration, and
seemed almost angry to find that he had already been frequently seen by Miss Lucas and herself.
His arrival was soon known at the Parsonage; for Mr. Collins
was walking the whole morning within view of the lodges opening into Hunsford Lane,
in order to have
the earliest assurance of it; and, after making his bow as the carriage turned into the park,
hurried home with the great intelligence. On the following morning he hastened to
Rosings to pay his respects. There were two nephews of Lady Catherine to require them,
for Mr. Darcy had brought with him a Colonel Fitzwilliam, the younger son of his uncle,
Lord ——; and, to the great surprise of all the party, when Mr. Collins returned,
the gentlemen accompanied him. Charlotte had seen them from her husband’s room, crossing the road,
and immediately running into the other, told the girls what an honour they might expect, adding,—
“I may thank you, Eliza, for this piece of civility. Mr. Darcy would
never have come so soon to wait upon me.” Elizabeth had scarcely time to disclaim
all right to the compliment before their approach was announced by the door-bell,
and shortly afterwards the three gentlemen entered the room. Colonel Fitzwilliam, who led the way,
was about thirty, not handsome, but in person and address most truly the gentleman. Mr. Darcy looked
just as he had been used to look in Hertfordshire, paid his compliments, with his usual reserve,
to Mrs. Collins; and whatever might be his feelings towards her friend, met her with every
appearance of composure. Elizabeth merely courtesied to him, without saying a word.
Colonel Fitzwilliam entered into conversation directly, with the readiness and ease of a
well-bred man, and talked very pleasantly; but his cousin, after having addressed a slight
observation on the house and garden to Mrs. Collins, sat for some time without speaking
to anybody. At length, however, his civility was so far awakened as to inquire of Elizabeth after
the health of her family. She answered him in the usual way; and, after a moment’s pause, added,—
“My eldest sister has been in town these three months. Have you never happened to see her there?”
She was perfectly sensible that he never had: but she wished to see whether he would betray
any consciousness of what had passed between the Bingleys and Jane; and she thought he
looked a little confused as he answered that he had never been so fortunate as to meet Miss
Bennet. The subject was pursued no further, and the gentlemen soon afterwards went away.
CHAPTER XXXI.